<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The araignement &amp; burning of Margaret Ferne-seede for the murther of her late husband Anthony Ferne-seede, found deade in Peckham Field neere Lambeth, hauing once before attempted to poyson him with broth, being executed in S. Georges-field the last of Februarie. 1608</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00692)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 724:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The araignement &amp; burning of Margaret Ferne-seede for the murther of her late husband Anthony Ferne-seede, found deade in Peckham Field neere Lambeth, hauing once before attempted to poyson him with broth, being executed in S. Georges-field the last of Februarie. 1608</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Henry Gosson, and are to be solde at the signe of the sunne in Pater-noster-rowe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1608]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>First leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Ferneseede, Margaret, d. 1608] --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Trials (Murder) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Araignement &amp; bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Margaret Ferne-ſeede,</hi> for the Murther of her late Husband <hi>Anthony Ferne-ſeede, found deade in</hi> Peck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Field neere Lambeth, hauing once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore attempted to poyſon him with broth, being executed in S. Georges-field the laſt of Februarie. 1608</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Goſſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the Signe of the Sunne in Pater-noſter-rowe. 1608</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13395:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:13395:2"/>
               <head>THE Burning of Margaret Ferne-ſeede.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He groſeſt part of</hi> folly, and the moſt repugnant, euen vnto our owne naturall reaſon, is to thinke that our hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den abhominations can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed from the eie of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, or that hee ſeeing our bloodie and crying ſinnes, will not either reueale them before his Miniſters of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique iuſtice, or in his beſt pleaſ'd time, power downe ſharpe vengeance for ſuch preſumptuous and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offences. Oh! the miracles in theſe Reuelations are ſuch, and ſo infinite, that the thought of man or his wiſdome is but meere weakeneſſe, going about to comprehend ſuch vnſpeakeable iudgements: &amp; of this wee haue before our eyes a moſt notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in this wretched woman, of whome my preſent diſcourſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth, named <hi>Margaret Ferne-ſeede,</hi> a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that euen from her time of knowledge (if the generall report of the world, according to the old adage, may be taken for an Oracle) was giuen to all the looſeneſſe &amp; lewdneſſe of life, which either vnlawfull luſt, or abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable proſtitution could violently caſt vppon her,
<pb facs="tcp:13395:3"/>with the greateſt infamie, yea, and with ſuch a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and inreſpectiue vnchaſtitie, that neither beeing <hi>chaſte</hi> nor <hi>caute,</hi> ſhe regarded not either into what eare the loathſomneſſe of her life was ſounded, or into what bed of luſt her laſciuious bodie was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported: in this more then beaſtiall laſciuiouſnes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conſumed the firſt part of her youth, finding both the corruption of her blood to check the former heate of her luſt, and the too generall vglineſſe of her proſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to breed a loath in her ordinarie cuſtomers, being then confirmed in ſome more ſtrength of yeares, tooke a houſe neare vnto the Iron-gate of the Tower, where ſhe kept a moſte abhominable and vilde brothell houſe, poyſoning many young women with that ſinne wherewith her owne body long before was filthilie bebotched. From this houſe at the Iron-gate, ſhe was married vnto one <hi>Anthony Ferne-ſeede</hi> a Taylor, dwelling in Ducke-lane, but keeping a ſhop vppon Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-hill neare Carter-lane. This <hi>Anthony</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his neighbors, reputed to be both ſober and of verie good conuerſation.</p>
               <p>Now it hapned that ſome few monthes agoe in the fieldes of Peckham neare London, there was found a man ſlaine hauing his throate cut, a knife in his hand, golde ringes vppon his fingars, and fortie ſhillings in money in his purſſe, his woundes of ſo long continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that it was not onely corrupted, but there was alſo Maggots, or ſuch like filthie wormes ingendered therein, which gaue teſtimony to the beholders, that he had not ſlaine himſelfe in that place, as well becauſe the place was free from ſuch a ſpectacle the day before, as alſo that ſuch corruption could not proceede from a preſent ſlaughter. Againe, what the perſon ſlaine, no man knewe, both becauſe his phiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>omie was altered in his death, and becauſe his acquaintance was little or none in thoſe partes about Peckham: in the end, ſearching his pockets, and other parts of his apparaile, amongſt other notes and reckonings, they found an
<pb facs="tcp:13395:3"/>Indenture wherein a certaine youth which did ſerue him was bound vnto him: this Indenture gaue them knowledge both of his name, and of the place of his dwelling, whereupon, certaine diſcreete perſons of Peckham, ſent to Londdon to Ducke-lane, and inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the houſe of one <hi>Anthony Ferne-ſeede,</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to his wife the diſaſter and miſchance which had befallen her huſband, which her hardoned heart recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, not as a meſſage of ſorrow, neither did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grudging of an afflicted countenance gal her remembrance, but as if it had bene the report of ſome ordinarie or vulgar newes, ſhe imbraced it with an inreſpectiue neglect and careleſnes, &amp; demaunded inſtantly (before the meſſage would tell her how he dyed) whether his throate were cut, or that he had cut his own throate, as either know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or propheſing how he dide, yet to obſerue a cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or (as the prouerbe is) to carrie a candle before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, ſhe prepares herſelf &amp; her Seruant, in all haſte to go to Peckham to behold her huſband: &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way as ſhe went, it was her chance to meete with one of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands antient acquaintance, who feeling that in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which ſhe ought to haue felt in nature, began to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine her miſfortune, telling her ſhe had loſt a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; good huſband: ſhe whome the deuill now would not ſuffer to diſſemble, (though his greateſt art be in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation) told him her feare was, ſhe ſhold not heare ſo well of him: he wondring at her vngodly careleſneſſe, let her paſſe, when preſently ſhe met another of her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, who with like charitie to the former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to pittie her griefes, (though griefe was neuer fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from her heart) and to wiſh her thoſe comforts which are fit for affliction, but ſhe as careleſſe as before, gaue him (by the neglect of her words) true teſtimonye how far ſorrow was from her heart, which when he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he ſaid, why miſtris <hi>Ferne-ſeede,</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of a good
<pb facs="tcp:13395:4"/>husband ſo ſlightly to be regarded? for mine owne part, had ſuch a unſchance faine to my fortune, I ſhouldere this haue wept out mine eyes with true ſorrow: but ſhe quickely made him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwore, tut ſix, mine eyes are ill alreadye and I muſt now preſerue them to mend my cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes not to mourne for a husband: after that, in her going, the winde blowing the duſt in her face, ſhe takes her ſkatff &amp; wiped her eyes, &amp; ſaid ſhe ſhould ſcarce know her husband when ſhe ſaw him, theſe curtizan like ſpeeches made her acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celeaue her, &amp; wiſhed her more grace, ſo ſhe &amp; her boy came where the bodie was, where more for awe of the Magiſtrate then any terror ſhe felt, ſhe made many ſower faces, but the drineſſe of her braine would ſuffer no moiſture to deſſend into her eyes: many queſtions were asked her, to which ſhe anſwered with ſuch conſtancie, that no ſuſpition could be grounded againſt her: then was her boy taken and examined, whod liuered the abhomination of her life, and that ſince her mariage with his maiſter, ſhe had liued in all diſquietnes, rage, and diſtemperature, often threatning his life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryuing plots for his deſtruction: that ſhe had euer ſince her mariage, in moſt publique and notorious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, maintained a yong man, with whom (in his view) ſhe had often committed adultrie: that the ſame young ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſince his maiſters loſſe was fled he knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that his miſtris had euen then before the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of his maiſters death, ſould all his goods (as he ſuppoſed) to fly alſo after him whom ſhe loued: all theſe ſpeeches were not only ſeconded, but almoſte approued by ſome of her neighbors, which liued neare vnto her, inſomuch that ſhe was the ſecond time taken
<pb facs="tcp:13395:4"/>into a more ſtrict examination: wherein albeit ſhe could not denie any of her generall aſſertions, yet touching the death of her huſband, that ſhe forſwore &amp; renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the fact or practiſe thereof to be hers, with ſuch a ſhameles conſtancie, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee ſtrucke amazement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that heard her: in the end by authoritie of Iuſtice ſhe was committed to the white Lyon in Southwarke: during the time of which impriſonment, till her time of tryall, thinking to out face truth with boldneſſe, and ſin with impudence, ſhe continued out all her exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations taken before ſeuerall Iuſtices in her former denialls, and whereas the Rod of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment laid vppon others, is receiued as a gentle correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby to looke into themſelues, it was to her ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the bellowes of indignation then a temperer to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: rather a kinde of frenzie, then a cooler of furie, &amp; rather a pruoker to euill then a perſwader to goodneſſe, for ſhe was ſeldome found to bee in charitie with any of her fellow priſoners, nor at any time in quiet with her ſelfe, rather a prouoker then an appeaſer of diſſentions, given to much ſwearing, ſcarce praying but continually ſcoulding, ſo that ſhee was as hatefull to all them that dwelt with her in that her laſt home the priſon, as ſhee was to people of honeſt conuerſation, hauing deſerued the name of a Baud) while ſhe liued abroad.</p>
               <p>In this vnciuill order, ſpending her houres, the time of tryall comming on, (when ſuch offenders were to appeare before the earthly Iudge, to giue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of their liues paſt) amongſt many others, this <hi>Margaret Ferne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed</hi> was one and at the aſſizes laſt, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of law, ſhe was indighted, &amp; arraigned, the purpoſe of which inditement, was to haue practiſed the murther of her late huſband <hi>Anthony Ferne-ſeede,</hi> who as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was found dead in Peckham field nere Lambeth:
<pb facs="tcp:13395:5"/>to the indit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ment ſhe pleaded not guiltie, putting her cauſe to God and the Countrie, which were a credible Iurie paniled, and had there made their perſonall appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for that purpoſe: then were theſe ſeuerall witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes produced againſt her, namely of the incontinentnes of her life paſt, her attempt to poyſon her huſband before this murther, as alſo to prepare broth for him, and put powder in it, her ſlight regard of him in his life, and her careleſſe ſorrow for him after death: with other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as the flight of the fellowe whome ſhe had liued long in adulterie with all, her preſent ſale of her goods vppon her huſbands murther, as it may be iuſtly thought, with purpoſe to flie after him: on which lawfull euidence, ſhe was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted, &amp; after iudgement giuen her to be burned: and from thence ſhe was conueyed backe to the White Lyon, till the time appointed for her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13395:5"/>
               <head>How Margaret Ferne-ſeede ſpent her time in priſon, from Satterday, the day of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction, till Munday the laſt of Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, <hi>when in S. Georges fieldes ſhe was executed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEing come backe to the priſon, for the firſt night ſhe diſpoſed her ſelfe according to her ancient habit, being as it were ſo rooted, and accuſtomed to euil, that as euen death it ſelfe had not power to make her forget it, and endeuour a better courſe: but being at the ſame time in the priſon with her, three Gentlemen who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were condemned, and who, through the courſe of their liues had not taught them to liue well: yet the care of theirs ſoules remembred them to dye well theſe Gentlemen hauing heard how ill her life paſt had bene, and that her countenance was as reſolute, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned the keeper that they might haue her company, partly to inſtruct her, but eſpecially y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe might ſee them, &amp; by the reformation of their liues ſhe might learne to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her owne and as they did, to prepare her ſelfe fit for death: whoſe porſuaſion and wholſome counſells of their owne, with comfortable promiſes of our mercifull Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt to them that vnfainedly beleeue in him, and by vnfained repentance make way to their ſaluation, as alſo with threatning her with the terrible Iudgements of Hell which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that periſh through lacke of grace, they ſo wrought in her, ſhe was at last drawne to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of her former life paſt, and to repent her of the ſame. The forme of which was in this manner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:13395:6"/>
               <head>The Confeſsion and repentance of Margaret Ferneſeed, after her condemnation in the White Lyon.</head>
               <p>TO prepare the reader for this confeſſion of hers, know that I was credibly ſatiſfied, that when the heat of her fury was paſt, to which ſhe was much ſubiect vnto) ſhe a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wel ſpoken, offaire deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and good perſuaſion: and ſo to her confeſſion.</p>
               <p>To excuſe my ſelfe O Lord before thee, who knowes the conſpiracies of our thoughtes euen to the vtmoſt of our actions, (how euer ſo priuat or publikely committed,) were folly, or to iuſtifie my ſelfe were ſinne, ſince no fleſh can appeare pure in thy ſight: I here therfore, with proſtrate knees, &amp; deiected eyes, as vnworthie to looke vp vnto thy diuine Maieſtie, with a contrite hearte and penitent ſoule, alſo here voluntariely confeſſe, I am the greateſt of ſinners, which haue deſerued thy wrath and indignation: In this good manner ſhe proceeded, and withall ſatiſfied all that came, &amp; deſired to haue priuate conference with her, of the whole courſe of her life, that in her youth, euen from the age of aptneſſe, ſhe had bene a proſtitute, whore but growing into deſabled yeares, to pleaſe the looſe deſires of ſuch cuſtomers, ſhe after turned baude, a courſe of life more hatefull in tempting and ſeducing youth, then the other in committing ſinne: the one makes but ſpoile and ruyne of her ſelfe, and the other of a multitude, for (quoth ſhee) I my ſelfe haue had ten ſeuerall women retaining to my houſe for that purpoſe: ſome were mens wiues, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired thither both by appointment, and at conuenent houres, when their husbands might leaſt ſuſpect or haue knowledge of their abſence: and theſe women did
<pb facs="tcp:13395:6"/>I firſt tempte to their fall, ſome, by perſwading them they were not beloued of their husbands, eſpecially if I could at any time haue note of any breach or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent betweene them: others, that their husbands maintained them not ſufficiently to expreſſe their beauty, and according to their owne deſarts: of theſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing brought my purpoſe to effect, &amp; that I knew they had offended, I made this booty that they were as fearefull to offend mes, as their husbands ſhould haue knowledge of their offences: and theſe allowed mee a weekly pention for comming to my houſe, and durſt not at all times but finde opportunitie to come whenſoeuer my ſelfe or ſuch looſe friendes, whome ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had bene familiar withall, or now deſired to be acquainted with them, ſhould ſend for any of them, to ſupply my houſe, and make ſpoile of yong maides who were ſent out of the countrie by their friends, herewith hope to aduance themſelues: I went weekly to the Carriers, where if the maide liked mee, I ſo wrought with the Carrier that ſhe Aldomeleft me till I had brought her to be as had as I purpoſed, which effected, euery one of them I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to giue mee ten ſhillings a week out of their gettings: hauing as I ſaid ſildome leſſe then ten whoſe bodies and ſoules I kept in this bondage: Beſides I confeſſe I was a continuall receiuer of theft ſtollen: but in all this, as it was badly got, ſo was it worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed for nothing of it did proſpere with me, whereby (quoth ſhe) I acknowledge I haue deſerued death, and in the higheſt degree, but for this which I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, Heauen that knoweth beſt the ſecrets of our hearts, knowes I am innocent.</p>
               <p>But who knowes not that in euill, there is a like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence to deny, as there is a forwardneſſe to acte: in
<pb facs="tcp:13395:7"/>which we wil leaue here whom the law hath found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and hauing thus truly related her owne confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee proceed to thee manner of execution.</p>
               <p>Firſt onely touching the euidence of two Sailers, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Iurie at her arraignment: Among other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that was auailableſt to condemne her, this was one and the chiefeſt: during the time while ſhe kept a bad houſe about the Iron-gate: by Tower-ditch, there hapned a couple of Bargemen to come to reuell at her houſe with ſuch Gueſtes as ſhe kept to entertaine looſe cuſtomers, and hauing ſpent the whole day in large ryot and much expence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night being late, for that time they made their lodging there, they beeing a bed, it hapned that night (which was ſildome) her huſband came to make his lodging there alſo, and being cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered with his wife, but a wall betweene where theſe Bargemen lay, they could expreſlie heare them euerie word that paſſed betweene them, the effect of which: was, the reprouing of her for her had life, his perſwading her to amendment, which ſhe not willing to liſten vnto fell a ſcoulding at him, and ſo left both his bed and cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſome time paſſing.</p>
               <p>At laſt Maiſter <hi>Ferneſeede</hi> heard theſe Barge-men cough, &amp; wondring to haue ſtrangers lodged in his houſe (for it was not common to his knowledge) aroſe out of his bed, and demanded of them what they were? who aſked of him alſo wherefore hee queſtioned them? mary (quoth hee) for if you be honneſt men, and haue a care either of your bodies or ſoules, avoide this houſe as you would doe poiſon, leaſt it be the vndoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of you all, they ſeeing him of a comely perſonage: and that his wordes tended to ſome purpoſe, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him what he was that gaue them ſuch wholeſome counſell? I am (quoth he) the maiſter of this houſe
<pb facs="tcp:13395:7"/>(if I had my right) but I am bard of the poſſeſſion and commande thereof, by a deuiliſh woman, who makes a ſtewes of it to excerſice her ſinnefull practiſes: ſo with ſome other admoniſhment left the roome, when theſe Barge-men tolde miſtris <hi>Ferneſeed</hi> what they had heard of her huſband, to which ſhe replyed: ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him ſlaue and villaine: I will before God bee reuenged of him (nay ere long) by one meanes or other, ſo worke, that I will bee rid of him, which making good in the iudgement of the Iudge, to gather with her life &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, ſhe as aforeſaid was condemned.</p>
               <p>On Munday being the laſt of February; ſhe had notice giuen her, that in the after-noone ſhe muſt ſuffer death, and a Preacher commended vnto her to inſtruct her for her ſoules health, who laboured much with her for the confeſſion of the fact, which ſhe ſtill obſtinately denied, but made great ſhowe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for her life paſt, ſo that about two of the clocke in the after-noone ſhe was ſtripped of her ordinary wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring apparell, and vppon her owne ſmocke put a kirtle of Canuaſſe pitched cleane through, ouer which ſhe did weare a white ſheet, and ſo was by the keeper deliuered to the Shreue, one each hand a woman leading her, and the Preacher going before her. Being come to the place of execution, both before and after her faſtning to the Stake, with godly exhortations hee admoniſhed her that now in that minute ſhe would confeſſe that fact for which ſhe was now ready to ſuffer, which ſhe denying, the reeds were planted aboute, vnto which fier being giuen ſhe was preſently dead.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
